A Guide to the Papers of Howard W. Smith 1901-1972 (bulk 1933-1966).
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Howard W. Smith 1901-1972 (bulk 1933-1966)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8731-b
This collection consists of ca. 650 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from Howard W. Smith on December 9, 1976.
Scope and Content
This addition to the Papers of Howard W. Smith consists of ca. 650 items, 1901-1973, including correspondence, speeches, statements and interviews, printed matter, memorabilia, photographs, blue prints for the Jefferson Memorial in Washington, D.C. and a map of U.S. postal routes in Virginia. Most of the correspondence and subject files date primarily from 1961-1968 and deal with the 1966 primary campaign for Smith's renomination to his Congressional seat (in which he was defeated by George Rawlings) and with Virginia's Eighth Congressional District Democratic committees and conventions, 1961-1968. In addition, there is material on the Department of Health, Education and Welfare school desegregation guidelines (1966) and a folder of miscellaneous correspondence. Correspondents include political figures such as Albertis S. Harrison, Jr. and Mills E. Godwin, Jr., and other federal, state and local officials and Virginia Democratic Party leaders. There are also public opinion letters on school desegregation.
The speeches, statements and interviews range from 1933 to 1966. There are compilations of Smith's voting record in Congress (1932-1966) and mailing and voting lists, probably from ca. 1946-1964. The memorabilia, 1901-1971, includes several certificates, resolutions, commissions, diplomas and awards; identification cards; a pen used by the President to sign H.R. 32220; medals from Democratic national conventions, 1960 and 1964; and, a resolution of the West Virginia House of Delegates on the death of Smith's sister, Lucy Montgomery Smith Price in October 1970.
Arrangement
When the collection was received, material was in no discernible order in the original folders. The original headings were retained. The collection is arranged by subject and is subarranged chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- 1966 campaign 1966 (Box 1)
- 1966 campaign 1966, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  Re George C. Rawlings, Jr.
- 1966 campaign 1966 (Box 1)
  Re George C. Rawlings, Jr. after primary
- 1966 campaign newsclippings 1966 (Box 1)
- Certificates 1930, 1932, 1968, 1971 (Box 1)
- Eighth District Democratic committees 1961-1968, n.d. (Box 1)
- Eighth District Democratic Congressional convention, Fredericksburg, Va., 1964 April 25 1964 (Box 1)
- Eighth District Democratic Congressional convention, Fredericksburg, Va., for 1968 May 4 1962-1964 (Box 1)
- Eighth District Democratic Congressional convention, Fredericksburg, Va., for 1968 May 4 1965-1968, n.d. (Box 2)
- Papers re George W. Grayson, Jr. and Fauquier County Democratic Committee 1964-1968, n.d. (Box 2)
- H.E.W. school desegregation guidelines 1966, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Identification cards 1965, n.d. (Box 2)
- John J. Moorcones newsclipping n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous correspondence 1963, 1966, 1973 (Box 2)
- Newspaper clippings and magazine articles 1961-1969, n.d. (Box 2)
- Photographs of Smith and others n.d. (Box 2)
- Speeches by Smith 1933-1966 (Box 2)
- Speeches, statements, interviews by Smith and others 1939-1965 (Box 2)
- Congressional Record remarks by Smith 1951-1966 (Box 3)
- Speeches, statements, interviews by Smith and others 1966-1967, n.d. (Box 3)
- Should the Republican Pary oppose Howard W. Smith in November by Robert O. Elder 1964 May 15 (Box 3)
  Student paper
- Transcript of television interview by Howard K. Smith on CBS Reports 1961 January 19 (Box 3)
- Voting list, A-W [ca.1946-1964?], (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Voting list for Virginia Highlands precinct, Arlington, Va. [ca.1946-1964?] (Box 3)
  Also includes miscellaneous petitions and correspondence.
- Voting mailing list for Fairfax, Arlington, and Alexandria, Va. [ca.1946-1964?] (Box 3)
- 18 individual voting records by roll call in the U.S. House of Representatives 1932-1966 (Box 4)
- Bachelor of Arts diploma, Bethel Military Academy 1901 June
- Bachelor of Law diploma, University of Virginia 1903 June
- Law license, Commonwealth of Virginia 1904 January
- Certificate of appointment as judge of the Corporation Court of the City of Alexandria, Va. 1922 October
- View of the proposed Thomas Jefferson memorial [1938], (4 items)
- Contract No. 4 General Construction and Mechanical Work for the Superstructure of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial 1939 January 18, (34 sheets)
  Architectural, structural and mechanical drawings
- Pen used by President Harry S. Truman to sign a District of Columbia-Virginia boundary act 1945 November
- Certificate of appointment to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia 1956 February
- Honorary badge, Democratic National Convention 1960
- Honorary badge, Democratic National Convention 1964
- Certificate of commendation from the House Committee on the District of Columbia 1966 October
- Certificate of Services, U.S. Congress 1967
- Resolution commemorating the death of Lucy Montgomery Smith by the West Virginia House of Delegates 1971 February
- Resolution on Smith's 89th birthday from the House Rules Committee 1972 January
- Photograph with greeting from Senator Hubert Humphrey n.d.